One thing about me that's not so good is that I often show up late to social things if there's a party.
关于我的一件不太好的事情是，如果有聚会，我经常在社交活动中出现迟到。
I'm often there 20 or 30 minutes late.
我经常迟到 20 或 30 分钟。
I know that's not good.
我知道那不好。
But for some reason I just have a difficult time getting to social things on time.
但由于某种原因，我很难按时参加社交活动。
And when that happens there are a few expressions that my friends might use with me to express either
当这种情况发生时，我的朋友可能会和我一起使用一些表达方式来表达
that they don't understand why I'm so late or perhaps just to express some impatience some impatience
他们不明白为什么我迟到了，或者只是为了表达一些不耐烦一些不耐烦
or maybe a little bit of frustration at my lateness.
或者对我迟到有点沮丧。
So what could we say here.
那么我们可以在这里说什么。
Well if it's not frustration and I'm late then I just got there and you were worried about me and you
好吧，如果不是沮丧，我迟到了，那么我刚到那里，你担心我和你
maybe are thinking is he going to actually show up is he going to be here.
也许在想，他会不会真的出现，他会不会在这里。
And then I do when I'm late.
然后我迟到了。
OK so someone might say you made it you made it you made it.
好的，所以有人可能会说你做到了，你做到了，你做到了。
And that's a happy expression positive.
这是一个快乐的积极表达。
That's to say you're here you arrived doesn't mean you've actually made something.
这就是说你在这里你到达并不意味着你真的做了什么。
It means I recognize that you are here.
这意味着我承认你在这里。
Hey you made it.
嘿，你成功了。
It's very positive.
这是非常积极的。
OK but but if it's a little bit of frustration that I'm late then someone might say What took you so
好的，但是如果我迟到有点沮丧，那么有人可能会说是什么让你如此
long.
长。
What took you so long.
你怎么这么久。
And this can be used in lots of different places lots of different cases lots of different situations
这可以用于很多不同的地方很多不同的情况很多不同的情况
where something happens later than it probably should have.
发生的事情可能比它应该发生的晚。
Maybe it's a task.
也许这是一个任务。
For example I ask you to go and get the umbrella from the other room and it takes you five minutes.
例如，我请你去另一个房间拿伞，这需要你五分钟。
You come back five minutes later and I say Hey what what what took so long.
你五分钟后回来，我说嘿，什么花了这么长时间。
What took you so long.
你怎么这么久。
I'm expressing a little bit of impatience there or if I show up 30 minutes late to the party and the
我在那里表达了一点不耐烦，或者如果我迟到了 30 分钟参加聚会，
host is there waiting for me because I'm the one who brought the wine for example and everybody's waiting
主人在那儿等我，因为我是拿酒来的，每个人都在等
for the wine.
为酒。
Then the host might say What took you so long.
然后主持人可能会说你花了这么长时间。
Now that's a rhetorical question.
现在这是一个反问。
Remember the meaning of a rhetorical question.
记住一个反问句的意思。
It's a question that doesn't really need an answer.
这是一个不需要回答的问题。
I could I could say yes I'm sorry I'm late.
我可以说是的，对不起，我迟到了。
We got a little bit stuck in traffic.
我们有点堵车了。
That's an excuse.
那是一个借口。
OK.
好的。
But this one doesn't actually have to be answered.
但这实际上不必回答。
We're not actually asking why are you late.
我们实际上并没有问你为什么迟到。
It's often just an expression of the feeling of frustration or impatience at my lateness and it can
这通常只是对我迟到感到沮丧或不耐烦的一种表达，它可以
be used in many many many many many ways.
以许多许多许多许多方式使用。
Another one that similar to this is where were you.
另一个与此类似的是你在哪里。
Where were you.
当时你在哪里。
This one is very similar to what took you so long.
这与你花了这么长时间的事情非常相似。
But there is a difference.
但是有区别。
So what's the difference between what took you so long and where were you.
那么你花了这么长时间和你在哪里之间有什么区别。
Well if we say where were you.
好吧，如果我们说你在哪里。
We're talking about being at a place stuck in traffic for example an explanation for not arriving somewhere
我们谈论的是在交通堵塞的地方，例如没有到达某个地方的解释
on time.
准时。
This one is usually specifically for a rival being somewhere whereas this one What took you so long
这个通常是专门针对某个地方的竞争对手而这个是什么花了你这么长时间
might be used for other things.
可能用于其他事情。
What took you so long.
你怎么这么久。
Could be about a task.
可能是关于任务的。
You didn't finish a task on time an assignment a paper homework so that sort of thing going to get something
你没有按时完成一项任务，一份作业，一份纸质作业，这样的事情就会有所收获
for example it could be about maybe response to a question maybe I take 30 seconds to respond to your
例如，可能是对一个问题的回应，也许我需要 30 秒来回应你的问题
question then I say something you could say Well what took you so long.
问题然后我说一些你可以说的东西 W是什么花了你这么长时间。
So what took you so long as more general and I would say much more useful in lots of other situations
那么是什么让你更笼统了，我会说在许多其他情况下更有用
besides just this party situation whereas that where were you is more specifically related to a rival
除了这个聚会的情况，而你在哪里更具体地与竞争对手有关
being there.
在那里。
OK so that's really the difference between them although in this case they're used in the same way.
好的，这确实是它们之间的区别，尽管在这种情况下它们的使用方式相同。